Guide to the Jerome Medalie Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Jerome Medalie papers
1965-2003
1965-1974
MS 1783
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
Correspondence, memoranda, writings, and printed materials primarily documenting the work of Jerome Medalie to effect legislation enabling the public financing of political campaigns in Massachusetts, and nationwide. An unpublished manuscript, "Private Financing of Political Campaigns: Time For a Change," is included in the papers.
Medalie, Jerome
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jerome Medalie, 2000, 2002, 2003.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Jerome Medalie graduated from Yale University in 1945. He served in the United States Naval Reserves on active duty in the Pacific during World War II. After the war, he completed a degree at Harvard Law School. Most of his legal career has been spent in private practice. In the early 1960s, Medalie became actively involved in Democratic politics in Massachusetts, creating the West Suburban Democratic League in the Boston area. His attention focused on the need for legislation dealing with the reform of political campaign financing. In the late 1960s to the mid 1970s, Medalie participated in the drafting of house bills proposing public funding of political campaigns and the preclusion of private contributions.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, memoranda, writings, and printed materials primarily documenting the work of Jerome Medalie to effect legislation enabling the public financing of political campaigns in Massachusetts, and nationwide. An unpublished manuscript, "Private Financing of Political Campaigns: Time For a Change," is included in the papers.
Campaign funds -- Law and legislation -- United States; Campaign funds -- Massachusetts; Campaign funds -- United States; Medalie, Jerome; Common Cause (U.S.)
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  The files are arranged chronologically. An item level index to the collection prepared by Jerome Medalie is located in Folder 1.
  - Index [descriptions of items in chronological order] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1967
    - Jan [ includes "Private Financing of Political Campaigns: Time For a Change"] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Feb-May (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Jun-Dec (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1968
    - Feb-Jul (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Aug-Oct (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Additional documents, 1973, 1991-1995, 2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Additional Material, Accession 2003-M-036
  General note
  Litigation involving Massachusetts House Speaker Thomas M. Finneran and the state Board of Bar Overseers.
  Also includes Accession 2004-M-019, 2004-M-029
  - Clean Elections Law, Massachusetts [includes email, correspondence, clippings, court documents], 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
  - Articles and commentary by Medalie on labor law as applied to employees and faculty of higher education institutions, 1970-2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Legal Status of Faculty Unionization in the United States," Handbook of College and University Administration, 1970
    - "Employee Relations and Unions," The International Encyclopedia of Higher Education, volume 6, 1977
  - Papers concerning establishment of the Jerome Medalie '45W Endowment fund at Yale University, 2000-2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Thou Shalt Honor [play in two acts, by Medalie], 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "The Pariah Image of the Lawyer: Symptom of an Endangered Vision of America?" Massachusetts Law Review, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)